טוב, tov,
thank you to anybody to the person who bought me the coffee.
Today's דף daf is ק"ו. kuf vav. We start with the next
משנה mishna
and again we're dealing with somebody sells land to his friend and
says, you know, it's a בית כור beis kor more or less,
it's a בית כור beis kor exactly, it's a בית כור beis
kor exactly more or less, more or less exactly. Anyway, so here
we have a different language that he can use and how much
you can be off. So it says, בסימניו ובמיצריו. besimanav uvemetzarav.
Let's say he sells it to him sort of like, you know,
when אברהם Avraham bought שדה עפרון, sadeh Ephron, right, it says very
clear exactly right, השדה וכל עץ אשר בשדה אשר בכל, haSadeh vechol
etz asher basadeh asher bechol, right, השדה אשר במכפלה אשר לפני ממרא
השדה והמערה אשר בו וכל העץ אשר בשדה אשר בכל גבולו סביב,
haSadeh asher baMachpelah asher lifnei Mamre haSadeh vehamarah asher bo vechol ha'etz
asher basadeh asher bechol gevulo saviv, right, no very specific. You spell
out exactly
here's the edge of this boundary, and here's the edge of that
boundary, and it's drawn right here, and you're very precise. Okay, so
then, but the משנה mishna ק"ו עמוד א'. kuf vav amud aleph.
Where are you? ק"ו. kuf vav.
Okay now, but you also say and it's a בית כור. beis
kor. Okay, and it's not exactly בית כור, beis kor, but you're
very exact what the boundaries are. So in that case, because you're
very precise about the boundaries, so it's really very clear what it
is you're selling, that is a little bit more weighty than the
claim of בית כור, beis kor, because presumably anybody can go ahead
and just measure and figure it out. So in that case you're
allowed more tolerance of being off before it has to be corrected.
So before we so in פחות משתות הגיעו, pochos mishtus higio, anything
that if you're off less than a sixth, which is obviously a
number we know from אונאה, ona'ah, but it's not an issue of
אונאה ona'ah here, because here it's again there's no אונאה ona'ah by
קרקעות, karkao'os, it's not a question of overcharging, it's a question of
what is the size of the object that you're giving. But anyway,
it's obviously an amount that's borrowed from that.
So so up to a sixth the guy has to swallow it,
whether it's the seller or the buyer who is off. עד שתות
ינכה, ad shtus yinake,
but up to a sixth you have to deduct. Now that's a
very strange language, up to a sixth. What it should have said
is a sixth and more you have to deduct. Okay, maybe it's
so that's why there's going to be a whole debate how to
read it. It could mean that anything more than a sixth you
have to deduct until you get to only being a sixth off,
but that's not clear either. If your overage is more, until now
we've been learning that you once you go past the tolerable limit
you have to correct the entire difference, right? So here too, you
know, you would sort of expect that that you would have to
correct the entire difference. Also, so it's not clear the language of
עד שתות ינכה. ad shtus yinake. The other thing is that how
do you make the correction? If you undersold the guy, like he
gave him
less land than a בית כור, beis kor, you would give him
a discount if you were the seller. Let's say the amount was
significantly more than a בית כור, beis kor, more than a sixth,
right? So before we discussed the idea that in principle you should
give back the land, but the seller has the option of demanding
the money instead of the land, right? Here it would seem to
me that since you're very precise about the boundaries,
there should be no option of giving back the land. You know
you very clearly sold something within these boundaries, so if the guy
gave significantly more than a בית כור, beis kor, the buyer would
have to sort of pay the difference, right? We discussed that before,
you might but there would not be like an option, I mean
if both sides agree געזונט הייט, gesunt heit, but there would not
be that one side could have unilaterally said I'm giving back since
it was very precise. Okay, so this is when you're very precise
and therefore it allows more tolerance because the claim of בית כור
beis kor is less weighty than the claim of the of the
parameters. And again, this is as opposed to if you said בית
כור beis kor more or less where there you're only allowed to
be off one twenty-fourth. This you're allowed to be off one-sixth, as
the רשב"ם Rashbam says, that is כפלי כפליים kiflei kiflayim from one
twenty-fourth, exactly it's four times more tolerant, one-sixth and one twenty-fourth. Okay,
alright, so let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara because the
vague thing here is like what's the story of about exactly a
sixth, what does it mean עד שתות ינכה? ad shtus yinake? So
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אתמר, itmar, it was
taught. רב הונא אמר שתות כפחות משתות, Rav Huna amar shtus kepochos
mishtus, that if you're off by a sixth it's like being off
by less than a sixth and that's tolerable and therefore you don't
have to make any correction.
רב יהודה אמר שתות כיותר משתות, Rav Yehuda amar shtus keyoser mishtus,
no, a sixth is like more than a sixth and you have
to correct for that as well. And now we're going to see
how they read the משנה, mishna, because the משנה mishna is inherently
ambiguous. It's hard to say there's a big principle difference between them,
right? Exactly which side of the line a sixth falls on, but
it's a question about how to read an ambiguous משנה. mishna. רב
הונא אמר שתות כפחות משתות, Rav Huna amar shtus kepochos mishtus, a
sixth is like less than a sixth. הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, here's
how you read it. פחות משתות. pochos mishtus. שתות בכלל הויא. shtus
bichlal hevia. Less than a sixth, if you're off by less than
a sixth and or by a sixth, then you have to swallow.
Now that's a hard read of the משנה. Mishnah. It says "less
than a sixth", right? Up until... so the רשב"ם Rashbam says that
according to him, he really reads the משנה Mishnah although this isn't
clear from the גמרא, Gemara,
פיחת משתות, piches mishtos, not פחות משתות, pachos mishtos, but פיחת משתות,
piches mishtos, if he reduced it by up to a sixth, okay,
by a sixth. So anyway, so that's included. If you're off by
less than and including a sixth, then the guy has to swallow
it. Okay, פחות משתות כבשתות בכלל הויא, pachos mishtos k'bishtos bichlal hevia,
יותר משתות ינכה, yoser mishtos yenakei, more than a sixth he has
to, so instead of עד שתות ינכה, ad shtos yenakei, he's reading
it יותר משתות ינכה yoser mishtos yenakei which is again hard to
read the language עד שתות, ad shtos, but anything, anything that's higher
than a sixth, the way he would read it is anything that's
more than a sixth up until and not including, one way to
explain their debate is a classic עד ועד בכלל ad v'ad bichlal
or עד ולא עד בכלל. ad v'lo ad bichlal. עד Ad is
inclusive or not inclusive. So if you read the last line עד
שתות ינכה ad shtos yenakei means, if you're up, if you're over
by a lot, any amount you're over, assuming a large amount over,
until you get to a sixth, you have to deduct. Now until
and including a sixth you have to deduct, or until you get
to a sixth you have to deduct but once you're a sixth
it's acceptable. Right? You understand? So if you think about it, right?
What?
A sixth is a large percentage, a sixth is like
16.6 percent, right?
That's what we said because you are very, I said it a
few times, because you are very specific about the boundaries. That's the
focus of what you're selling. The claim how big it is is
seen as more secondary than the clear definition of what you're selling.
So if this is the base amount, right, and this is a
sixth, right, and here's the amount that's like more than a sixth,
right, here's half off, or whatever, anyway, so it says no matter
if you're off no matter until you get עד שתות, ad shtos,
then you have to deduct. And the question is when you get
to exactly that line of a sixth, any amount you're off until
you get to being a sixth off you have to deduct. Now
is it until and including a sixth you have to deduct? Too
little? Too high, too high. This is a hundred dollars,
and here it's 116 and 2/3 dollars,
and here you're selling it for 200 dollars, and here you're selling
it for 150 dollars. So if you're more, not 150, it's not
dollars, excuse me, it's acres, okay, it's whatever it is, it's a
סאה, se'ah, okay, here it's fine, sorry. Here it's one סאה, se'ah,
but actually we're talking about, okay, here it's one and a sixth
סאה, se'ah, a כור, kor, oh for God's sake, one and a
sixth כור, kor, okay, here it's one and a half כור, kor,
here it's two כור. kor. Okay. So if you're off, actually if
this path has you being off that you undersold the guy not
oversold the guy, but fine, we're going to do it this way
because it's easier with the math. If you're off a lot until
you get it to being a sixth off, you have to correct
the price, right? Once you're a sixth then it's tolerable. So until
you get to a sixth you have to deduct. What if you're
exactly at a sixth? Do you have to deduct or is that
the tolerable amount? So it's how do you read the עד שתות?
ad shtos? עד Ad is עד ad inclusive or not inclusive.
So that's רב הונא'ס... Rav Huna's... yeah, one suggests the משנה Mishnah
is רבי ירמיה, Rabbi Yirmiyah, that's clear.
Yeah, okay fine.
Would you say, would you read this סוגיא sugya as a kind
of חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני? chisuri michsera v'hachi katani?
No, I would read it as...
it reads like that.
Yeah, well that's why the רשב"ם Rashbam claims the first line really,
the first approach is really not פחות pachos but פיחת, pichet, but
it's a lot of it is, yeah, and a lot of it
is it's a vague משנה, Mishnah, you know? And a lot of
it is how to read the עד. ad. עד Ad is inclusive
or not inclusive. Wait, let me just read this again so it's
clear. הכי קאמר, Hachi qamar, פחות משתות ושתות בכלל הויא. pachos mishtos
v'shtos bichlal hevia.
If you're off anything less than a sixth, including a sixth, then
you have to accept it, right? יותר משתות, Yoser mishtos, if you're
anything more than a שתות shtos that you're off, and עד שתות
ad shtos includ- I mean sorry, עד ad and not including, up
more than a sixth and not including a sixth, okay, עד ולא
עד בכלל ינכה, ad v'lo ad bichlal yenakei, then it has to
be deducted and adjusted. רב יהודה אומר Rav Yehuda omer שתות כיותר
משתות. shtos k'yoser mishtos. No, no, a sixth is like more than
a sixth and that also has to be adjusted. והכי קאמר, V'hachi
qamar, this is clearly the better read of the משנה. Mishnah. פחות
משתות הויא, Pachos mishtos hevia, less than a sixth you have to
swallow it. עד שתות Ad shtos any amount more than a sixth
and up to and including a sixth, עד שתות ושתות בכלל ינכה,
ad shtos v'shtos bichlal yenakei, then you have to deduct it. That's
clearly a much easier read of the משנה. Mishnah. Yes Michael?
You mean like way too much, right?
Yeah, or way too little, whatever.
You say בית כור, Beit Kor, wouldn't the logical interpretation be not
you've gained way too much but they just took it? And then
he was like, no, I meant a בית כור Beit Kor in
these borders.
No, I think that's why סימנא דמיצרי simana d'meitzarei is very clear.
Its northern border is here, its southern border is here, there's absolutely
no question what the plot of land is, and it's very clear.
No, no, I don't know. That's, whatever, we're not talking about that
case. That, that can be claimed. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this: מיתיבי, Meisivei, I'll ask you on this.
Where were
we? בסימנא ובמצרא פיחת שתות או הוסף שתות. besimana u'metzra picheis shtusa
o hosif shtusa. Now here it's a ברייתא Braita that instead of
פחות משתות pichos mishtusa has the גירסא girsa of פיחת, picheis, right?
He went a שתות shtusa less or a שתות shtusa more, okay?
הרי הוא כשום הדיינין, harei hu keshum hadayanim, that is like the
assessment that דיינין Dayanim make. Now this which is going to lead
us, I'll warn you, into a complete digression when we're now going
to spend the rest of today's דף daf very soon discussing how
דיינין Dayanim make their assessment. Okay, but anyway, but the point is,
you know,
חנן Chanan there owes me, owes me a thousand dollars. He has
no cash on him. He's not giving the money. He has no
cash on him. I'm going to go seize his property. So we
have to get an independent assessment about how much his property is
worth. So some judges come down, a בית דין Beit Din comes
down, and they assess his property, okay? And they determine, you know,
this plot of land is worth, you know, a thousand dollars, and
I take it. And then it turns out that they were off.
I don't know how it's decided that they were off. Somebody else
comes, they realize they made a mistake. Right, that's always a question:
how do you know that they were off? But anyway, so what
being off is tolerable? And we would say, no, that was the
assessment that they made, and I took it with that dollar value
assigned to it, and whether I lost out or you lost out,
we have to just accept that. And at what stage do we
say they were so off that we have to reassess its value
and redetermine how much of my debt now has been paid off?
So the basic principle is: up to a sixth, it's a tolerable
amount for them to be off, and then that's a binding dollar
value that's assigned to it. And more than that, it's an invalid
assessment and we have to reassess the value.
No, no, no, no, no. They misassessed the value. At the time
they assess it, it's now determined that they were too much off,
that they were not, yeah, that they were not. It was a
matter of negligence. They were negligent, right? They didn't notice something, right,
something of that nature. Yes.
So I'm just realizing this now. Would you say it's accurate to
say that that concept of what a judge does is really different
than what דיינין Dayanim did in the גמרא? Gemara? In other words,
a judge wouldn't come and do a land assessment. Right, he'd have
a specialist do that and give.
Yes, I was wondering about that too. And we're actually, you know,
going, like, you know, can they deputize
specialists? And the גמרא Gemara is going to give us a case
where they actually are independently coming and assessing. But, you know, you
have like patent lawyers and patent judges that have real specialization in
the substantive area, industry, in which they're judges of, you know?
דיינין Dayanim were more like the range, a diverse range of expertise
amongst lawyers than it is.
Maybe. I mean, it's a good point. Like, right, would you have,
in order to be a judge, would you have to be able
to assess קרקע? karka? Or would you have specialized בית דין Beit
Din that you would go to for that purpose? I would assume
the latter, but yes, I was wondering that too as well.
But yes, דיינין Dayanim could mean anyone under the auspices of the
בית דין.
Beit Din. Well, I know, except we're going to see that it's
going to be a case where it's going to talk about the
דיינין Dayanim themselves. But yes, I could imagine that they could also
deputize certain experts. Okay, so let's take a look. It says now,
if you're off when you're selling this land in this case, so
if you're over or under by a sixth, בסימנא ובמצרא פיחת שתות
או הוסף שתות, besimana u'metzra picheis shtusa o hosif shtusa, הרי הוא
כשום הדיינין, harei hu keshum hadayanim, it's just like an assessment of
the judges. הגיעו, higiau, and you have to accept it. Now, of
course, this is a self-contradictory language, because an assessment of the judges
is, a sixth is invalid. So this says if you're off by
a sixth, more, you know, you're over or under a sixth, it's
like the amount of the assessment of judges, which is a sixth,
הגיעו, higiau, and you have to swallow it. The only problem is
that the assessment of judges is negated, you know, is voided at
a sixth. So we're going to bracket the word הגיעו higiau for
a moment, and we're going to say, look, it's saying that you
can be off by a sixth. So the גמרא Gemara says, והא
שום הדיינין כשתות כי יותר משתות. ve'ha shum hadayanim keshtusa ki yoseir
mish'tusa. We know when it comes to the assessment of judges, a
sixth is like more than a sixth, and it voids the assessment.
So, and so you see that a sixth is tolerable, because it
says if you're off by a sixth, you swallow it, and it
links it to the assessment of judges. So that means
if you're off by a sixth, it's
voided like the assessment of judges, so you see it's invalid. אמר
לך רב הונא, amar lach Rav Huna, so רב הונא Rav Huna
says to you, ולטעמיך הגיע קתני. u'l'ta'ameich higia katani. What do you
mean? You try to say that by the comparison to the judges,
it shows that a sixth is like more than a sixth and
it's voided, or it would have to be corrected, but the end
of that ברייתא Braita says you have to swallow it. So what
are you talking about?
אלא כשום הדיינין ולא כשום הדיינין. ella keshum hadayanim velo keshum hadayanim.
Clearly what the ברייתא Braita means
is, it's comparing it partially to the assessment of judges.
כשום הדיינין לשתות, keshum hadayanim leshtusa, it's like the assessment of... assessment
of judges in the sense that a sixth is the relevant amount,
we're just using that to signal that we mean a full sixth
and not under a sixth. But the לא כשומא דדייני, lo k'shuma
d'dayani, but it's not the same הלכה, halacha, דאילו התם ביטול מקח
ואילו הכא הגיעו, d'ilu hatam bitul mekach v'ilu hacha higiyu, there it's
voided and here actually you have to swallow it. Okay? So it's
actually a very funny ברייתא, braita, compares it to the case of
the judges where we know that a sixth is voided and it
says and you have to swallow it. So what the now it's
sort of being read to emphasize the הגיעו, higiyu, the פסק psak
which makes sense and to say actually this is a proof that
a sixth is tolerable. Okay. The רשב''ם Rashbam tries to figure out
how it would like or whatever has a different גירסא girsa to
the גמרא, Gemara, how it would read to read it consistent with
the approach that a sixth is voided, that it really is fully
like שומא דדייני, shuma d'dayani, but anyway the simple sense here is
that it is like this, it's like it's being read right here,
that it's only similar in that a sixth is a relevant amount
but it's the opposite הלכה. halacha. It's actually that here that it's
tolerable as opposed to there where it's voided. Okay.
Rebbe, is this statement here equating בטל batel with ינתן? yinaten?
Well, yes in the sense
that and the word בטל batel bothers...
Right. So that's why, right, so it's in it's associating it in
the sense that it becomes not a tolerable not tolerable being off
by that amount.
What you thought was a closed deal is בטל batel because it
needs to be adjusted.
Right. So how do you deal with a non-tolerable variance? By the
case of the deal it's by doing a by by adjusting the
price or whatever and by the case of the judges it's doing
a reassessment.
My economic lens... I know. That's why the רשב''ם Rashbam which is
coming from some other completely different context.
Well it's true. The רשב''ם Rashbam reads, just so you should know
that the way the word to read the way he reads the
word הגיעו, higiyu, he says this is actually what the גמרא Gemara
is saying. The way he words to read the word הגיעו higiyu
to be consistent with the approach that you have to adjust it
is that as opposed to שומא דדייני shuma d'dayani where the whole
thing is בטל, batel, here הגיעו higiyu the sale is still valid.
But you still have to adjust it. But it's obviously the opposite
of the word הגיעו higiyu in the משנה.
Mishna. כאילו שומא דדייני. ke'ilu shuma d'dayani.
Something. Well הגיעו higiyu the base the the actual transaction. Anyway let's
move on. Okay. רב פפא זבין ארעא מההוא גברא. Rav Papa zavin
ara me'hahu gavra. רב פפא Rav Papa bought land from a certain
person. אמר
ליה הוי עשרין גריוי. amar leh havi esrin girive. He said to
him that this is twenty גריוי girive big, okay, so משחה
ולא הוי אלא חמיסר, mashche v'lo havi ella chamisar, and then he
measured it and it was only fifteen. גריוי girive is a measure.
Yeah, yeah it's a certain measure. I think סאה.
se'ah. What do you see? גוריי באני השטח. goraye b'anei ha'shetach. Comes
off like an arrow.
What? It says it's a סאה? se'ah? Yeah, that different word. Okay.
Anyway yeah that's fine I think it's a different word.
גריוי. girive. Okay.
Anyway, so they talk to each other in Babylonia. There's a different
word for the same thing.
I know. Anyway, so he said so the guy said to him
it's twenty and then he after he brought it he measured it
was fifteen. So he wanted to get an adjustment because that's off
by more than a sixth, that's off by a third. אתא לקמיה
דאביי. ata l'kamei d'Abaye. אמר ליה סברת
וקבילת, amar leh savarta v'kabilta, I guess
anyway you have assessed it and accepted it, meaning you knew what
you were getting into and you were okay with it. Now of
course now that's right it ignores what we talked about until now.
והתנן פחות משתות הגיעו עד שתות ינכה. v'hatnan pachot m'shisus higiyu ad
shisus yinake. Okay and that even when the boundaries of the land
are very clear and explicit and nevertheless it's only tolerable by up
to a sixth. הני מילי היכא דלא קים ליה בגוה, hani mili
heicha d'lo kam leh b'gavah, that's only when you didn't know what
the measurement was. So then you didn't know and you were sort
of relying on the assessment. Okay then then it has to be
adjusted. אבל היכא דקים ליה בגוה aval heicha d'kam leh b'gavah apparently
this is a case where you knew that it was fifteen. The
guy was claiming twenty but you all along knew that it was
fifteen. I don't know how אביי Abaye knows that. So in that
case סבר וקביל, savar v'kabil, so you you assessed it and you
accepted it. So then what did he think when the guy was
saying twenty? Why did he want a discount? So apparently the way
the רשב''ם Rashbam explains the case is he was saying like I
know it's fifteen but you're claiming it's twenty. So you're claiming it's
twenty and you're asking for me for I don't know for two
thousand dollars, which means that you're implicitly promising me that if it
is not twenty and it's off by more than a sixth, because
that's the rules, you as the seller you don't know actually how
much your acreage is. I know your acreage better than you do.
And you're promising me it's twenty and you're setting a price or
we agreed upon a price. So I'm going to interpret that as
an implicit promise that if it's off by more than the tolerable
amount you're going to adjust the price. So I'm not finding it
in my interest to correct you right now and after the fact
I'm going to correct you and I'm going to want a price
adjustment.
That's the רשב''ם. Rashbam.
That yeah, that's the way the רשב''ם Rashbam explains how he could
say I knew what it was and now I'm still asking for
an adjustment. Yes I knew what it was but I was working
with his assumption of his claim of how much it was and
the price to now entitle me to an adjustment based on that.
what it actually is. And the answer is no, you know, since
you weren't in error, you knew what the with the acreage was
and you agreed to the price, you can't now be looking for
an adjustment, okay, which is very interesting. I don't know how you
assess that the person knew,
but that becomes an interesting principle in הלכה halakha which is like
סבר וקיבל savar vekibel which applies in a wider range of cases,
like if somebody makes a stipulation in a תנאי tnai or normally
we say that if I don't know something has a מום, mum,
it's a basis for being ביטול מקח bittel mekach but if you
were aware of the מום, mum, right, you know, like I sold
you a car and you saw that it had a dent here
or whatever, you looked at it whatever and you agreed to the
thing, you now can't come back and tell me you want a
ביטול מקח bittel mekach cause I don't know the dent was worse
than you thought it was. You know, like you saw it, you
assessed it, you implicitly agreed to those conditions. Yes.
קים ליה בגוויה kim leh bagava means he measured it?
Yeah. Yeah.
Okay. And so how do you translate קים ליה בגוויה? kim leh
bagava?
To know about its, you know, you were you know about what
about what it is, like you have an I'm trying to look
at the like the קים kim like you've assessed it, you were
there.
Right, you were there, you were in the field.
Right, but it's more abstract, like you've like like you know what,
you know, you've you're standing... yeah, you know what you're getting into.
Like you're yeah, you know the reality that's confronting you. You know,
you know the reality that's confronting you. What?
Basically on top of that the fellow was selling him at the
price that he wanted to have it at then.
Right, if he told him, "Hey, it's only 15," and then the
guy would have said, "Well, the price is still the same," so
it wasn't in his interest to correct him then, it was only
in his interest to correct him afterwards, right. How do they translate
קים ליה בגוויה? kim leh bagava? קים ליה בגוויה kim leh bagava
means like you're I think you're right, I think it means like
you're you know you're standing in it but like you know you're
you're קים
ליה בגוויה kim leh bagava
you know you're confronting the reality.
Yeah, familiar with the field, familiar...
What? Familiar with the field, being so... You know what you're looking
at. Okay. All right. So okay. והא עשרים אמר לי, v'ha esrim
amar li, so but he said 20, which means that from his
perspective he thought it was 20 and that was the price for
20. So now that it's 15 I should get an adjustment of
the price. So אמר ליה דעדיפי כעשרים, amar leh de-adivi ke-esrim, nah
he means we're going to interpret it to mean that this is
I know it's 15 סאה sa but it's worth 20 סאה. sa.
So you know, so we're not going to say that he actually
means that, which is interesting, you know, because it's right it's like
this is funny this is why also like you want like these
deals to be dealt with more by what objectively people are saying
and more that's in their mind, because like who now the court
has to figure out what's going on in your mind. Like we're
saying yes you said you know you said 20 but you all
along knew it was 15, right. So now you're telling me that
I don't have a right to claim an adjustment because you're figuring
out what was in my mind. Okay, so let's figure out what
was in his mind too, you know. And it's like it's funny
like why we decide to reinterpret you know his language and why
don't we decide to say he objectively said 20.
Yes. So that question stands, but given the ambiguity here, it's easier
to understand I think the perspective of the seller to me this
than the buyer. What buyer would go into a deal overpaying purposely
in order to get a refund, rather than a seller meaning you
know I'm going to sell you this and it's really worth that.
That makes at least somewhat more...
I don't know.
Right, right, right.
I see the buyer going into it saying he's going to sell
me a small amount, he's going to tell me large amount, again
I get him in the door and then lower the price after.
Yeah, I mean in my mind the bigger question is how do
we determine what that you knew all along that it was 20.
I mean do we have direct witnesses that heard you say, "Hey,
guess what this guy thinks it's 20 אמות amot but it's really
only 15," which is really bizarre if you want to actually cheat
the buyer whatever, you want to get the better of the... I
mean the better of the seller is when they think it's less
and it's really more. But anyway, but you said to your friend,
"I'm going to go buy ראובן's Reuven field it's like 15 סאה,"
sa, and then you now you're coming a day later to the
court and said he told me it was 20. But like how
do you know unless you directly heard it from the person? Yes.
And what if the fact of the matter is he really he
didn't have this in his mind, he discovered later?
So then presumably it would be adjusted. Presumably the case is that
אביי Abaye somehow knew that he knew all along what it was,
you know. So it's an interesting caveat to what we've been saying
but hard to know how to assess it.
Okay. And hard to know what you do if the seller actually
said like let's say let's just stop for a moment and say
that you didn't have the ability to reinterpret the language of the
seller, right. Let's say that you knew somehow the seller absolutely believed
that it was 20 and this guy absolutely knew and we have
evidence of both that it was 15. Okay, would he be entitled
to an adjustment or not? Right. Like the גמרא Gemara doesn't resolve
that. You know it's 15, you know he was selling it under
the belief like what happens when... and you can't reinterpret the language
of the seller. So I don't know what to do. All right,
anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on: תניא, Tanya, רבי יוסי
אומר, Rabbi Yose Omer, האחים שחלקו. Ha'achim Shehalku. Now we're going to
get to an interesting sort of side issues, but based on the
fact that we mentioned like שום הדיינים Shum Hadayanim and other types
of things, okay, האחים שחלקו, Ha'achim Shehalku,
actually שום הדיינים Shum Hadayanim is coming tomorrow, I jumped ahead. So
we'll get I mean we'll get to that. But anyway, האחים שחלקו,
כיון שעלה גורל לאחד מהם קנו כולם. Ha'achim shehalku keivan she'ala goral
l'echad mehem kanu kulam. So basically brothers inherit an estate
and there are let's say three fields, you know, and they have
three brothers and they have to let's ignore the issue of בכור
bechor and they have to let's say decide which one gets which
field. So what they do is they draw a lot, okay? And
so as soon as they draw lots, so that somehow is going
to operate to divide the estate, which is very interesting. Where do
we ever hear that, you know, that drawing a lot is a
way to give you a portion in land? You should have to
do a קנין. kinyan. So actually though, it is the way they
divided the land when they went right, it is the way they
divided the land when they went into the land of Israel initially
with יהושע. Yehoshua. But does that work in future cases of קניינים
kinyanim and so on? Okay, so but partly also what makes this
easier is that maybe you don't need a full חזקה, chazakah, a
full act of קנין kinyan is that they all already do own
it in partnership. So the drawing of the lots is more like
especially if you believe of יש ברירה yesh breira type of an
idea, you know, determining which plot maybe always was mine or at
least anyway the land is more, you know, it's easier to divide
because you don't have to take it away from somebody, you just
have to define what your section is as opposed to another section
is. So there's an assumption here that after everybody drew lots, the
land would be divided accordingly. That would suffice, that you didn't need
a קנין. kinyan. But here what happened was only one person drew
lots and the other two brothers did not. Does that guy get
his portion and or does nobody get any portion until everybody draws
the lots? Okay, so that's the question. So let's take a look.
האחים שחלקו Ha'achim Shehalku, כיון שעלה גורל לאחד מהם קנו כולם. keivan
she'ala goral l'echad mehem kanu kulam. Once one of them drew his
lot, so then the other two, now they haven't subdivided it, but
now, you know, the רשב"ם Rashbam says now the other two could
actually divide it in a different way. So ראובן שמעון ולוי, Reuven
Shimon v'Levi, you know, or you know whatever put you know the
numbers one, two, three in the box. You know ראובן Reuven drew
out number three, so ראובן Reuven gets field number three. שמעון ולוי
Shimon v'Levi now jointly own field number one and two. If they
want, they can continue the drawing of lots, and if they want,
they could just decide between the two of them how to divide
it. Okay?
These are like discrete fields?
Yes, they've identified, if it weren't a discrete field it doesn't matter,
they've drawn out lines and identified this will get lot one gets
this piece, lot two gets this piece, lot three gets this piece,
and now let's draw. Okay? So once,
so מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Now what's the reason? The way the
רשב"ם Rashbam explains it is like I get when all three of
them do it, then somehow it's like,
like we said somehow maybe either learned from the model of how
they divided the land of Israel or somehow because in general it's
like since they all own it jointly, this is a if they
define this as a way of dividing it it'll work. But when
one of them does it and they haven't fully divided it, why
does that work?
So מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? אמר רבי אלעזר כחלקת ארץ ישראל, Amar
Rabbi Elazar k'chalukat Eretz Yisrael, like the division of the land of
Israel. מה תחילה בגורל אף כאן בגורל. Ma techila b'goral af kan
b'goral. The same way there it's with a lot, here too it's
a lot. So אי מה להלן בקלפי ואורים ותומים. ee ma lehalan
b'kalpi v'urim v'tumim. One minute, there it was specifically with certain types
of lots, I mean it's also I don't know the difference between
גורל goral and קלפי. kalpi. קלפי Kalpi is just like the קלפי,
kalpi, they were the קלפי? kalpi? קלפי? Kalpi? קלפי. Kalpi. Yes. Okay,
fine.
A Greek word meaning a jar or box.
Okay, so the box that they sort of put the lots in.
So and they had the אורים ותומים, Urim v'Tumim, that was a
bigger difference.
Okay, אף כאן בקלפי ואורים ותומים? af kan b'kalpi v'urim v'tumim? So
maybe it all has to be like it. How do you know
you can learn it out from there? So אמר
רב אשי בההוא הנאה דקא צייתי להדדי גמרי ומקני להדדי. Amar Rav
Ashi b'hahu hana'ah d'ka tzayti l'hadadi gamri u'makni l'hadadi. No, with the
sort of the benefit that they're all agreeing that this is how
they're going to divide and they're all have agreed that they will
like go by the lot, then that creates the sufficient like גמירת
דעת, gemirat da'at, full intent, full willingness to make the deal final
through this act. Now, this is an important idea because you know
normally
the גמרא Gemara right needs a form two things normally comprise what
allows you to take possession of something. Number one is a formal
מעשה קנין, ma'aseh kinyan, הגבהה, hagbaha, משיכה, meshika, or by land it's
חזקה, chazakah, plus the willingness of the buyer to buy and the
seller to sell, or if there's only one side like it's הפקר,
hefker, the intent to take possession. But you need דעת, da'at, you
need the intent to create the transaction, and you need the act
that that signifies the transaction. Okay. Under some cases you need much
less of a... act because you have a stronger דעת. daas. The
classic example of this is חליפין, chalipin, right? חליפין, chalipin, the act
of like the handkerchief or whatever, that almost certainly like is a
generic type of a thing. It doesn't signify ownership like הגבהה hagbahah
or חזקה chazakah does. It's more like a handshake. It signifies your
that you have, you know, גמירות דעת. gmiras daas. You know, what,
your resolve to do it and your finality of your commitment to
do it. Okay, and therefore it works generically for a wide, wide
range of things. Sometimes we even say that you might be able
to do something with pure גמירות דעת gmiras daat without any act
whatsoever. Okay. What? Yeah, no, no, but that's a little different and
that's closer to this. But sometimes what we allow is almost a
you can sort of like, you know, make your own מעשה קניין
maaseh kinyan because fundamentally it's not about again demonstrating ownership. It's an
it's a thing that demonstrates גמירות דעת. gmiras daas. Your, you know,
your conviction and that and that it's final. And therefore if that's
agreed within a context like this thing about like, you know, if
if everybody of a certain trade agrees that a certain act shows
that the deal is final, like with the example everybody always gives
is when you say מזל וברכה mazel u'vrachah in the diamond district,
right? Then that works, because that's like a type of a חליפין.
chalipin. That's just some expression of גמירות דעת gmiras daas that's agreed
upon. Okay.
So so that seems to be the point here, that he says
like since we've all agreed upon it and we're all like we're
all committed that this is going to finalize it and then presumably
then this act actually that we've agreed, this drawing of the lot
actually does it. It doesn't say you can do it without the
drawing. It does well, okay, but presumably each act, you know, is
enough by itself. That's part of the חידוש. chiddush. The
it doesn't say that we just agreed סתם. stam. If we all
got together and said, "Good, are we all agreed this is the
division? Yes." Like that wouldn't be it. We would have to do
a handshake, or we'd have to do קניין חליפין. kinyan chalipin. You'd
have to do some type of an act, but we've agreed that
this is the act. Now the רשב"ם Rashbam says, now you again
you could sort of explain that that's why it works even when
all three draw. As I said, it's interesting that the רשב"ם Rashbam
somehow says, "No, no, you didn't need this גמרא Gemara for all
three of them. You only need this גמרא Gemara for one of
them." Like to me it would be like you need this explanation
even for the case of all three of them to explain what
the mechanics are and why it works. The other interesting thing the
רשב"ם Rashbam says is is he says that this answer is only
supporting the argument or or sort of combined with the argument that
this is what they did when they divided ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Why? Because he says, he says, "I'd really like to say that
this is even without that argument, that you could do something other
than lots. You could I don't know what you could do. You
could I don't know what you'd do, flip a coin or throw
darts at a dartboard or something. Who knows what you could do.
You know, ask somebody pick a number from one to three or
something. I don't know. But," he says, "because the גמרא Gemara doesn't
have the word אלא, ella, the גמרא Gemara has the word אמר
רב אשי amar Rav Ashi and it doesn't say אלא אמר רב
אשי," ella amar Rav Ashi, he says, "I'm forced to say that
Rav Ashi's argument is just in combination with the previous one." Important
difference, right? When it says אלא, ella, "rather," says so and so,
it means it's a completely different answer. When you don't have the
word אלא, ella, it means that it's modifying the previous answer, not
a different one. So there's a very powerful language in the רשב"ם.
Rashbam. The רשב"ם Rashbam says like this, if you look at one,
two, three
lines down in the wide lines, he said,
he said, "כך זקוק אני לפרש." kach zakuk ani lefareish. He
said, he said well, maybe we'll start from the whole piece. אמר
רב אשי. amar Rav Ashi. It's the end of like the last
of the middle sized lines in the רשב"ם. Rashbam. לעולם כתחילת ארץ
ישראל קונה גורל, leolam ketichilas Eretz Yisrael koneh goral, it does work
on the basis of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, כאורים ותומים. ke'urim ve'tumim.
והקשה לך
אם על הלה וכו' היינו טעמא דלא צריך כולי האי. ve'hakashah lecha
im al halan ve'chu' haynu taama d'lo tzarich kulei hai. Here why
don't we need all of that whole apparatus, the אורים ותומים, urim
ve'tumim, the קלפי, kalpi, etc.? משום דגמרי ומקני למי שיהיה עליה גורל
מיד מהני גמירות דעתם עם
הגורל כאורים ותומים. mishum digmarei umaknei lemi sheyiheyeh aleha goral miyad mahani
gmiras daatam im hagoral ke'urim ve'tumim. This substitutes the absence of the
אורים ותומים. urim ve'tumim. The גמירות דעת gmiras daat takes the place,
the agreement takes the place of the apparatus of the אורים ותומים.
urim ve'tumim. But it's still fundamentally based on the model of ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. דמהני אפילו היכא דלא גמרי ומקני דבההוא הנאה דצייתי
ומשמעים זה לזה לחלוק בגורל כדי שיהא כל אחד חלקו בפני עצמן
ואינם חפצים עוד בשיתופות. demahani afilu heyca d'lo gamrei umaknei de'behu hana'ah
ditzayti umashmim zeh lazeh lachalok begoral kedei sheyehe kol echad chelko bifnei
atzman ve'einam chafetzim od beshitufoos. It's clear they want to divide up
the partnership and therefore that גמירות דעת gmiras daas works in the
place of the apparatus, but it's to combines with the model of
the
גורל. goral. כך זקוק אני לפרש. kach zakuk ani lefareish. I'm forced
to explain it this way. שהרי אין כתוב בספרים אלא אמר רב
אשי. sheharei ein kasuv basfarim ella amar Rav Ashi. It doesn't say
"rather," says Rav Ashi, which would mean this explanation stands by itself.
הלכך לא בא לסתור טעם מורי רבי אלעזר אלא לתרצו. hilkach lo
ba listor taam mori Rebbe Elazar ella letartzo. He's only coming to
modify it. Which means that according to this, if you did something
that wasn't with a גורל, goral, some other type of way, it
wouldn't work unless you did a חזקה, chazaka, right? So because he
says it has to base itself on the model of תחילת ארץ
ישראל, techilat Eretz Yisrael, yes. Go ahead.
I have two questions if you don't mind. One is just to
clarify, what actually is happening? There's three people, they're dividing this field.
One person draws a lot. How do the other two divide the
remaining?
Either they continue to draw lots or they decide on themselves, you
know what, let's just the two of us stay in partnership, although
I don't know if that would work, or let's just, you know
what, actually given that we're left with this piece, I prefer the
north side, you prefer the south side, fine. They could do it
on their own, right?
But they still need to draw lots themselves?
Yeah, they could do a separate drawing of lots, they could do
whatever they want.
But the second thing is, as you've suggested in other contexts, sort
of the transposition of מקדש, Mikdash, you know, model and theology into,
you know, so is this suggesting here that anytime Jews divide a
piece of property in a business deal or through inheritance there's an
incipient theological model of reenacting the drama of the tribes' inheritance?
Ah, you're suggesting that, which is beautiful, but the question is that
רב אשי Rav Ashi was an אמורא, Amora, a Babylonian אמורא. Amora.
So you're right that it's almost a little funny, or
or he's yearning for the application.
Yeah, but now applying that dividing a plot of land that we've
got in New Jersey is like dividing a plot of land in
ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. We've done that all the time for two thousand.
Yeah, but isn't it problematic sort of seeing that as our like,
modeling that after ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? One, you could say it's
a yearning for ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, the other is just deciding
that it's like, like you know, Vilna's like the, you know, ירושלים
Yerushalayim of the. Right, I know. So right, it's an interesting point.
You know, I had a, yeah, it's a very good point, yeah.
Okay, there's a bunch of רבי אלעזר.
Rabbi Elazar. רבי, Rabbi, okay, yeah. Why am I not surprised? רבי
אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, I was wondering about that. Is רבי אלעזר Rabbi
Elazar ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or or בבל? Bavel?
Charlie should know that. Charlie's going to look it up.
What we're saying is the other two then don't have to continue
the lots since the lots sort of broke the ground. Then the
then the two can flip a coin?
Yeah, exactly. No, the other two would have to do in a
way that in a way that still was halachically a legitimate division,
but they wouldn't have to continue on with this process. You know,
they would still have to do a חזקה chazaka or their own
drawing of lots or whatever whatever would generally.
I think the north piece and the south piece, that's not true.
Oh, then they'd have to do like a קנין סודר kinyan sudar
or something like that to finalize. Exactly.
But I wonder what the etymology of lot and lot, we're using
lot and a lot of land. Yeah, that's a good point. Alright,
it's a good
point. Okay. Now. איתמר שני אחים שחלקו בא להם אח ממדינת הים.
Itmar, shnei achim she-chalaku, ba lahem ach mi-medinat ha-yam. Now this is
why we started by introducing this thing before, because this has nothing
to do with us, because now we're going to introduce, but we
wanted to discuss
dividing an estate to get to this case, which is tangentially going
to have to do with us. Okay. So, two brothers divided the
estate they inherited, and then some long-lost brother came from overseas and
he said, yeah, remember when your father was on that trip to
Hong Kong 20 years ago? Well, I'm the result. So anyway, and
he's able to bring evidence that he's their brother. Okay, so.
And
you get over the shock.
Right, exactly. And now I want, I want my part of the
inheritance. Now the thing is they already had drawn lots and divided
it. How are they supposed to adjust the inheritance
accordingly? Okay. So רבא אמר בטלה מחלוקת. Rava amar batla machaloket. The
whole thing is voided and you have to start again. ושמואל אמר
מקמצין מקמצין. U-Shmuel amar mekamtsin mekamtsin. That you you like do you
you do like, you do
like קמיצה kmitza like a handbreadth, like you you you know you
collect from the other two and you carve out, that's a good
that's an excellent word, you carve out from the current division to
give the guy his plot. Now the problem, the question is, and
so what רשב"ם Rashbam says, it literally means it, you know, these
ראובן ושמעון Reuven ve-Shimon both got you know plots. I mean, if
you want to sort of look at it this way, let's do
it this way. Okay.
There were these two plots. You know ראובן Reuven got this amount
and שמעון Shimon got this amount. So the most fair thing you
would sort of say is that you'd sort of do this to
give him that. But the רשב"ם Rashbam makes it sound like it's
up to ראובן ושמעון Reuven ve-Shimon to decide. And if שמעון Shimon
wanted to give him this and ראובן Reuven wanted to give him
that, he'd be stuck with two plots which would be very not
fair. Even if they agreed to do this, that might not be
fair. Right? Maybe this is the worst land, maybe this who knows
what it is? He could say, hey, you guys got... to either
you either did it by drawing lots and you did it by
consensus, or either you did it by drawing lots or you did
it by consensus, but everybody had an equal shot. Why do I
get it to be, you know, pre-determined? So the רשב"ם Rashbam says
like, nevertheless, the רשב"ם Rashbam says that's what שמואל Shmuel means. When
he says you carve it out, we keep this fixed, that was
good at the time it was good, it remains good, and we
find a way to give him the third plot. I mean, at
least what I would sort of do is I would say you
got to get a בית דין Beis Din involved to make sure
that, you know, even if he doesn't have much choice, at least
he's getting something that's considered fair.
Okay? But and I think the רשב"ם Rashbam says that, if I
remember correctly, the רשב"ם Rashbam says that there's a בית דין. Beis
Din. Hold on, let me see. נותן כל אחד שליש מחלקו ונותן
כל. Noten kol echad shelish mechelko venoten kol. No,
he doesn't say a בית דין. Beis Din. בית דין Beis Din
comes later. בית דין Beis Din comes later. תוספות Tosafos does not
like this at all. תוספות Tosafos says this is completely unfair and
how can you do that and how can you leave it up
to their choice, especially if you leave it up to their choice.
So what תוספות Tosafos says is when he says מקמצים, mekamtzim, what
it really means is the following: is that he gives a scenario,
let's again assume that you have these three
fields, one, two, three. So he took one, he took two, and
he took three. So תוספות Tosafos says what you actually do, I
mean this is so not פשט pshat in the גמרא, Gemara, but
תוספות Tosafos is really bothered with the unfairness of it. So what
תוספות Tosafos says is what you actually do is you draw lots
again. Okay? That's the only fair way is that you draw lots
again. So let's say we drew lots again and לוי Levi got
this one. Great! Then you could leave the previous division as it
was. You would not continue like beyond that. People would sort of
be kept with at least partly the previous division would have been
stable. Let's say instead לוי Levi got this one. Okay? So then
what you might just do in that case is just move שמעון
Shimon over here, because then at least partly of the original division
stands. ראובן's Reuven part stands, right? And שמעון Shimon gets half of
what he originally got. So how do you מקמצים mekamtzim then according
to...? But it's somehow you draw lots but you try to keep
the original division as much as possible. How do you do that?
Well, I just showed you how you do that.
Or I was reading תוספות.
Tosafos. Yeah, well if if לוי Levi got this, then לוי Levi
takes a half from each and that's then that's then you're able
to keep most of the original division. If לוי Levi gets this,
then you move שמעון Shimon over here, so שמעון Shimon gets half
of part of what he already got. ראובן Reuven gets where he
already got. So you try you do like you you have a
draw lots and לוי Levi takes a lot and then you try
to keep the original division. Anyway, it's not פשט, pshat, but תוספות
Tosafos is really bothered with the question of how fair is this
that you know, you just carve out and he doesn't get an
equal section. Yes?
I just wondered, haven't we been saying that marriage has nothing to
do with a claim?
That is correct. That is correct. You mean because of my example,
the Hong Kong trip? Maybe maybe he married another wife there, maybe
who says it wasn't marriage. But the answer is correct. You know,
you know,
if somebody is a son even outside of marriage, it is not
the idea of bastard child in the in secular law in English
law whatever that only a child born within a legitimate marriage is
an heir. No, even if it's not born within a legitimate marriage,
he is an heir. Even a ממזר? mamzer? Even a ממזר mamzer
is an heir, right, which is pretty striking. Now on the other
hand, the counterargument to how is this fair is imagine that this
guy shows up 20 years later and these people have already totally
developed the land and they build skyscrapers and whatever, now we're supposed
to completely re-divide it? You know, so it's an interesting question of
how to like balance those issues. Yes.
Speaking of improvements, aren't those other גמרות Gemoras like how you...
Yeah, that is true, but nevertheless, it's not just, oh, it's just
trivial to re-do it. It's trivial to re-do it if he shows
up a day later. It's not trivial to re-do it if he
shows up years later.
I was just thinking of the English expression, right? I have a
lot of something.
Right. Lot? גורל. goral.
Exactly. Okay. No, we got to keep on moving. I'm sorry, it
doesn't matter. It doesn't matter. We're moving on. All right. אמר ליה
רבא לרב נחמן. Amar lei Rava le-Rav Nachman.
So רבא Rava said to רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. לדרב דאמר בטלה
מחלוקת, Le-Rav de-amar batlah machlokes, Rav says that you have to start
the whole thing over again. אלמא הדר דינא. Alma hadar dina. So
that means that the the judgment is you you reverse the judgment.
Now, that's a phrase that's used like by a בית דין. Beis
Din. A בית דין Beis Din פוסק paskens something, you realize a
mistake, to what degree does now once the rule once the judgment
was given, it stands or to what degree do you revoke it?
So we're borrowing that language because this obviously isn't a case of
דין, din, but it's basically means like that once that division was
made, it stands as much as is possible, right? I'm sorry, does
not. The other, הדר דינא, hadar dina, that we're prepared to revert
it when it's based on a mistake. אלא מעתה, Ela me'ata, if
that's true, הני בי תלתא דקיימי, hani bei tlata de-kaimi, so you
have three people that are partners. ואזול בי תרי מינייהו ופלוג, ve-azul
bei terei minaihu u-felug,
and two of them go and without the consensus consent of the
third person, okay, two people go and they say, you know what,
let's divide. divide this partnership that we've got. Okay, we all own
this big plot of land in partnership, let's go ahead and we'll,
I'll take this part, you take that part, we'll give Levy who
isn't here this third, this third part. Now here, of course, this
seems like tremendously unfair, so the רשב"ם Rashbam sticks in here that
we're talking that the בית דין beit din is involved. בית דין
beit din sort of assesses it and determines that each person is
getting a fair amount, but the third guy isn't there. Okay, so
he says, הכי נמי דבטלה מחלוקת? hachi nami d'batla machlokas?
Would you say there that if the third guy shows up, that
you should void it? Now of course I would say, yeah, I
think you should void it, I don't think that should have been
legitimate in the first place. Like even if a בית דין beit
din is involved, if you've got three partners, how do two of
them decide to make a division? So but somehow the גמרא Gemara
not only takes it for granted that the division would be legitimate,
it even says that like if the third guy shows up and
objects, that he has no say. So that's why the רשב"ם Rashbam
has to stick in that a בית דין beit din was involved,
but it still seems quite bizarre. So and so the גמרא Gemara
says, so there obviously it would still be legitimate. So how is
this different? So האכא השתא, hacha hashta, what kind of comparison is
that? התם נחיתי אדעתא דבי תלתא. hasam neichisa adata d'vei tlata.
There they knew that there were three of them and they divided
it understanding that there were three plots and again we're going to
totally read in what's not in the גמרא Gemara but the רשב"ם
Rashbam reads in and בית דין beit din was involved and בית
דין beit din decided that each one was an equal and a
fair division. So in that case, מעיקרא, mei'ikara, so
therefore they knew that there were three and it was all done
with that assumption. So there was no mistake. It's just the third
guy wasn't involved, but there was no mistake. התם נחיתי אדעתא, hasam
neichisa adata, האכא לא נחיתי אדעתא דבי תלתא מעיקרא. hacha lo neichisa
adata d'vei tlata mei'ikara.
Here they assumed there were only two of them. So the whole
division was in error. Okay, so that's clearly a difference, but I
think all of us would object to the idea that something like
that should be legitimate without the presence of the third party. But
anyway.
Was it intentional? They had, they didn't know the third brother existed?
That's what the גמרא Gemara says. It's not that they did something
wrong, it's that they were fundamentally in error, right? It's not that
they were like they were evil, they were fundamentally in error, so
therefore the whole thing was void. Right, here it's like the flip.
Here it's like they know there's a third party, they're ignoring him,
they're not involving him. On the other hand, right, they are dividing
it with an understanding of that they have to create three equal
sections. But again, that's why the רשב"ם Rashbam has to throw in
a בית דין beit din or else he says this doesn't make
any sense. Okay, but okay, let's keep on going. So it says
like this. Now
תוספות, Tosafot, now hold on
let me just check. Okay fine. Now so okay, so that's that
position. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר ליה רב
פפא לאביי. amar lei Rav Pappa l'Abaye. רב פפא Rav Pappa said
to אביי, Abaye, ושמואל דאמר מקמצין, v'Shmuel d'amar m'kamtzin, according to שמואל
Shmuel who says I like Michael's phrase, you carve out from the
existing
division, okay, למימרא דקם דינא, l'meimra d'kam dina, that seems to be
like this principle that a judgment stands, again borrowed this language from
בית דין. beit din. והא רב ושמואל דאמרי תרוייהו, ve'ha Rav v'Shmuel
d'amri tarveihu, כור בשלושים אני מוכר לך, kora b'shloshim ani mocher lach,
יכול לחזור בו אפילו בסאה אחרונה. yachol lachzor bo afilu b'sa'ah achronah.
Now we see a little bit how we're tying this in to
what we've got with before. If somebody says I am selling you
this כור kora for thirty, you know, סלע, sela, and you took
possession of twenty-nine, you can back out even until the last סאה
sa'ah because you didn't take full possession. Okay, כור בשלושים סאה בסלע
אני מוכר לך, kora b'shloshim se'ah b'sela ani mocher lach, ראשון ראשון
קנה. rishon rishon kanah. So now how is that relevant? So it's
relevant in the following way. The גמרא Gemara says that the same
way in this case שמואל Shmuel would say that even though שמעון
Shimon wound up taking more than what's his portion, he took up
one and a half units and ראובן Reuven one and a half,
okay, nevertheless we try to keep it as valid as possible, we
carve out the extra half, but we try to keep what's already
done as valid as possible. The same way that's true when you
took more than what's coming to you, he said logically it should
be true when you took less. I was trying to buy thirty,
I bought twenty-nine, okay, I didn't get the full thirty, but let's
let the קניין kinyan that I've done on twenty-nine be valid. Okay,
now of course you can make a lot of distinctions between those
cases, but that's the argument. If we're trying to say don't revert
things, things that were already done should not be reverted, you just
make adjustments. So here you made an adjustment that you took away
something. There you don't even have to take away, you just have
to say the twenty-nine you already did a קניין kinyan remains valid.
עד דמשייא. ad d'mishaya. Right, so why, so though, but that's not
only if you said a סאה sa'ah for
a סלע.
sela. סאה בסלע. sa'ah b'sela.
No, but okay, but if you said thirty for the whole thing,
it doesn't. Why not? Why not let? Yeah, exactly. Exactly. So the
גמרא Gemara says התם עבדו רבנן מילתא דניחא ליה למוכר וניחא ליה
ללוקח. hasam avad rabanan milta d'nicha lei l'mocher v'nicha lei l'lokei'ach. No,
in principle maybe you're right that using this logic of קם דינא
kam dina would be fine, but there given that the intent was
to sell the whole thirty units, we assume that either side because
they framed it that way wants the right to back out until
you finalize the sale. עד דמשייא. ad d'mishaya.
You have to have this in order for people to do business.
Right, so.
Maybe you're right that using this logic of קם דינא kam dina
would be final, but given that the intent was to sell the
whole 30 units, we assume that either side because they framed it
that way wants the right to back out until you finalize the
sale. In business, you have to have this in order for people
to do business. Right, exactly. So we're still left with this question
about once you did something and found out there was an innocent
error, how much you have to redo it all from the start
or how much you try to maintain what was already done as
much as possible. Okay, so you will continue with this to